Hello
喂
Hello, Grandpa?
喂，爺爺
Can I come stay with you
我可以去山上
in the mountains?
找你嗎
When I was little
小時候
I lived in the mountains
跟爺爺奶奶
with my grandparents
住在山上
Grandpa used to say
爺爺常常跟我說
Just look up at the starry sky
只要抬頭望著星空
and the whole world will seem so vast
世界就會變得好大好大
They're all modern French artists
都是一些法國的當代藝術家
Come any time
你隨時來
We have on-site commentators
我們當場都有解說員
No problem, just call me
沒問題你打給我
I'll wait for you there
我在那裡等你
No, it's really progressive
不會，非常有創意的
Who buys old paintings these days?
現在誰還買那些古畫
Modern art goes up in value
現在當今的藝術家，畫才會增值
Sure
可以
Next time there's an auction, we'll go
下一次有拍賣會的時候我跟你一起去
Hello
喂
Hello, Grandpa
喂，爺爺
Mei?
小美
Are you on the train?
妳在火車上
You went home?
回家了
I'm home
嗯，到家了
Mei
小美
Grandpa's wondering
爺爺很煩惱
what gift to make for you?
想不到做一件什麼禮物給小美
Oh
嗯
An elephant
一隻大象
A blue elephant
一隻藍色的大象
OK  I'll bring it when I come visit
好，爺爺下山就拿給妳
Grandpa
爺爺
Come soon
你要快點來
I really miss you
我好想你
Mom, what are you doing?
媽，妳在幹嘛
Travel stuff
出國的事
I'm leaving in two days
我過兩天要出國
I'll be back before New Years
過年前就回來
Again?
又要出國喔
Haven't started?
怎麼不先吃啊
Waiting for me?
在等我啊
Let's eat
開動開動
What do you think?
怎麼樣
It's silly
很蠢耶  蠢？
You're wearing a hat at the dinner table?
吃飯的時候戴什麼帽子
Mei
小美
Dad made sweet and sour pork
爸爸特別做了你愛吃的
your favorite
糖醋裏肌
Mei
小美  啊
What's wrong?
怎麼了
My trip to Paris is cancelled
我後天不去巴黎了
How come?
不去了？為什麼
Come on, tell me what's going on
喂，妳跟我說怎麼一回事
Can you just leave me alone?
你可不可以讓我靜一下
Come back and finish dinner first
…妳可不可以先回來吃飯
I need to be alone for a bit, please
我需要一個人靜一下，拜託
Please get out of my room
請你離開我的房間
Your room?
妳的房間？
When did it become 'your' room?
什麼時候變妳的房間了
When you put a bed in your study
從你把床弄進你書房的時候
What's that supposed to mean?
妳這是什麼意思
Let's not fight, OK?
我們不要吵了好不好
It's not that serious
事情沒有那麼嚴重啊
Yeah, it's never serious for you
對，對你來說永遠都不嚴重
it's always me
都是我…
Shall we finish the 'Starry Night' puZZle?
我們一起把星空拼完好不好
Mei, go back to your room
小美，你先回房間
I'll be there in a bit
等一下爸爸再陪你拼
All of us?
我們一起嘛
Be a good girl
小美乖
Go back to your room
先回房間
Good girl
乖
Merry Christmas
聖誕快樂
I don't know who you are
雖然我不知道你是誰
But I want to tell you
但是我想跟你說
Merry Christmas
聖誕快樂
OK, everybody
各位同學
Settle down
安靜安靜
Come on, Back to your seats
來，回去坐好
We have a new student
班上轉來一個新同學
Come on, come on in
來，進來進來
Introduce yourself
跟大家自我介紹一下
My name is Jay
我叫周宇傑
He's a bit shy
有點小聲
His name is Jay
他叫周宇傑
His last name is Chou
宇宙的宇
Jay Chou
傑出的傑
He's joining our class
剛轉來班上
Let's all help him settle in
大家以後要多多幫忙他
Let's give him a round of applause
大家掌聲歡迎他好不好
You can sit there
你坐那邊
Open up your books
課本翻開來
Shawn
陳威翔
What chapter are we on?
上禮拜教到哪裡啦
I don't have my textbook
不知道啦
You confiscated it last time
課本上次被你沒收啦
Through interacting with others
我們可以透過與別人的互動
We can better understand ourselves
來更加地瞭解自己
Discover our strengths and weaknesses
發現自己的優點和缺點
And gain a sense of balance
並試著找到標準來衡量自己
If we find our strengths
如果能夠發現自己的優點
we can use them
發揮所長
Build our self-confidence
便能夠增加我們自己的自信心
And unlock our potential
甚至激發潛能
You there!
這位同學
We're in the middle of a lesson
這位同學我還在上課
Where do you think you're going?
你要去哪裡
The bathroom
上廁所
You didn't think to ask?
要上廁所不會先問嗎
May I go to the bathroom?
老師，我可以去上廁所嗎
He's so cocky
有夠囂張的
Hurry back
快去快回
Everyone else
來，其他同學
Pay attention, let's continue
頭轉回來，我們繼續上課
Mei
小美
We're going for some crepes
我跟班長她們要去吃可麗餅
Want to come?
妳要不要一起來
I
我…
Come on, let's go
好啦！一起去嘛
I have to be home early
我今天要早點回家
Next time, OK?
下次好了
Next time
下次吧
What are you doing?
妳在幹嘛
Studying
做功課
Look what I bought you
看媽幫妳買了什麼
Hang it up for me
幫我掛那邊好了
No way!  Naked women!
哇靠！裸女耶
Shawn!  What are you doing?
陳威翔你幹嘛
Let me see
借我看一下
You can look and I can't?
自己看，我不能看喔
Check it what the new kid drew!
看新來的畫的
Go away!
你不要動
Stop it!
你不要鬧了
You guys, look!
歡，你們看
Look at the naked women!
新來的畫的裸女耶
Look!
你們看
Stop it guys!
喂！不要鬧了
Hey, Shawn
歡！陳威翔
What are you doing?
你在幹嘛
Looking at naked women
看裸女啊
Stop it!
你們在幹嘛
Class rep  What happened?
班長，怎麼一回事
He
他…
Shawn
陳威翔
What's that?
那什麼
Take a look yourself
不會自己看喔
Whose is this?
這誰的
His
他的
Don't take someone else's stuff!
你幹嘛拿人家東西！跟我出來
Jay
周宇傑
I'm sorry
對不起
None of your business
關你屁事
Miss Chang
張小姐
Jay's
宇傑的…
Jay's sketchbook
宇傑的素描
How should I put it?
該怎麼說
It's not that the school doesn't value art
學校不是不尊重藝術
It's just that, some of Jay's sketches
只是，宇傑有些素描
Can lead to some wrong thoughts
可能會讓一些同學
For the other students
產生不好的聯想
You know schoolboys
你知道初中男生
They're very immature
有些心智不太成熟
They can't tell the difference
繪畫裡藝術或者是情色的部份
Between art and pornography
他們比較不能夠辨別
Just as long as you teachers can
你們老師可以辨別就好啦
Jay won't bring that sketchbook
以後宇傑不會帶這樣的繪畫本
to school anymore
到學校來
Right?
對不對
You think you're cool?
再臭屁啊
Not so cocky now!
再臭屁嘛
Kick him!
踹他啦
You asked for it!
欠扁啊
Stop it!
住手啦
Let Jay go!
放開周宇傑
Are you okay?
你還好嗎
I'll survive
死不了
How many times have I told you
告訴你多少次
It is never OK to hurt a girl
打女人的男人不是男人
Mrs Chou
周媽媽
Jay never hit me
宇傑他沒有打我
Some boys were bullying me
是班上幾個男生在欺負我
Jay got hurt coming to help me
宇傑是來幫我的時候受傷的
Mom, let's go
媽，走了啦
Is someone picking you up?
有人來接妳嗎
Yes
有
Thank you
謝謝
The two of them
他們啊…
They were making out in an alley
在巷子裡面親熱
Totally shameless!
真是不要臉
No way!
太跩了吧
Shawn saw
陳威翔啊…
Dad
爸
Help me with this
幫爸爸拿一下
You went to see Grandpa?
你去看爺爺了
Mei
小美
Grandpa's sick
爺爺生病了
He's in the hospital
現在在醫院裡
This elephant
這個大象
was when I went to get Grandpa
就是爸爸去接爺爺的時候
he said to give it to you
爺爺叫我交給妳的
Can I go see Grandpa?
那我可以去看爺爺嗎
It's past your bed time
現在太晚了
Dad!
爸
Let Grandpa rest a bit
妳就讓爺爺多休息一下
I'll take you tomorrow
明天我就帶妳去
You coming too?
你也要來嗎
Come on
過來啊
Let's go
走吧
We'll go see Grandpa together
我們一起去看爺爺吧
Grandpa
爺爺
Mei
小美
Where's your Mom and Dad?
爸媽呢
You came by yourself?
一個人來的
You can have the elephant
這隻大象還給爺爺
I don't want it
我不要
When you get better
等爺爺病好了
Make him a fourth leg, then I'll take him
給牠裝上第四隻腳我才要
OK
好
Dad!
爸
Mom!
媽
We're going out
爸媽出去一下
Be a good girl, stay home
妳乖乖待在家裡
Mei
小美
We're leaving now
爸爸媽媽要出發了
You're really not coming?
妳真的不去嗎
You don't want to say goodbye to Grandpa?
妳不去跟爺爺說再見嗎
Don't force her if she doesn't want to
她不去就不要勉強她了
Hey, young lady!
歡，同學
Excuse me!
同學
Mei
謝欣美
You forgot to pay
妳忘了付錢了
About
那個…
The classroom decoration contest
班上的佈置比賽
Teacher asked me to do it
老師問我要不要做
I was wondering
我想說
Can you help me with it?
我想說妳可不可以跟我一起做
I can't finish by myself
我一個人應該做不完
OK
好啊
Really?
真的嗎
Morning
早
Good morning
早安
I drew it out, just follow the steps
我畫好了，妳就照著折就可以了
So now I'm up to
那我現在是折到…
Here
這邊
This one
這個
A bit to the left
左邊一點
Down a little
往下
Check it out
歡，你看那
Mei and Jay, they're at it again
謝欣美跟周宇傑不知道在幹什麼
Over there, being all lovey
又在那邊卿卿我我
Up a bit, over there
往上往那邊
That's good
對
Shawn, what are you doing?
陳威翔你幹嘛
This looks good!
很帥耶
Can I have it?
給我好不好
Looks good, just like me
跟我一樣帥
We match
很配我
Thanks!
謝啦
Give it back
還回來啦
There are so many animals
反正你這邊那麼多隻動物了
Elephants, squirrels, sheep
有大象松鼠還有羊
Let me have this one  Thanks
給我一隻，謝啦
Don't mess with other people's stuff
你不要一直拿人家的東西好不好
What!  I can't have it?
怎樣啦？不能拿喔
I'll take it if I want to!
在教室，就是大家的啦
What?
怎麼樣
Knock it off!
你幹嘛
What?  I dare you to hit me
怎樣啦？有種你打我啊
Too scared?  Go on
不敢喔！打啊
Give it back
還來啦
Shawn, stop it!
陳威翔，你不要鬧了
Keep at it and I'll get the teacher
再鬧我叫班導來喔
Call him, I don't care
來啦！不怕他啦
I'm not scared of him
叫他來
Stop it, Shawn
好了啦！陳威翔
Shawn, listen to the class rep
陳威翔聽班長的啦
Here we go again
又來了
He's always like this
真的很過分
So childish
煩不煩啊！幼稚
Shawn
陳威翔
Give it back
東西還來
Who wants these stupid things, anyway
誰要你們這種爛東西
Mom
媽
Get changed and we'll go eat, OK?
我們換衣服去吃飯好不好
Mei, did you get a boyfriend?
小美最近交男朋友了
Huh?
啊
No
沒有啊
You've been coming home late
我看妳最近都比較晚回家
I told you, I'm busy with the competition
跟妳說過我在忙教室佈置
Are you happy?
妳開心嗎
Whatever you do
反正不管做什麼事情
It's important to be happy
開心最重要了
Mom
那…
Are you happy?
媽媽妳開心嗎
Right now, I'm
我現在…
really happy
非常開心
Remember the dance I taught you
妳還記得小時候
when you were little?
我教妳跳的那個舞嗎
That step forward, step back
妳是說踩來踩去
clap your hands one?
拍來拍去那個嗎
Dance with me
陪我跳好不好
What?
啊
Here?
在這裡
Sure!
對啊
No!
不要啦
Come on!
來嘛
Ready
來囉
1  2 3 4 5 Jump!
一二三四五跳
Jump!
跳
3  Jump
三跳
1  2 3  Jump
一二三跳
This is Monet's 'Woman with a Parasol'
這是莫內畫的 撐傘的女人
The woman is his wife, Camille
女人是他的妻子卡蜜兒
The boy next to her is their son
旁邊這個小男孩是他們的兒子
This is 'The Lovers' by Magritte
這是瑪格利特的《情侶》
This is Van Gogh's 'Sunflowers'
這是梵谷的《向日葵》
This is
這是…
Renoir's 'Luncheon of the Boating Party'
雷諾瓦《船上的舞宴》
How do you know all this?
你怎麼知道這些
My Mom studied art in Paris
我媽媽以前在巴黎就是學藝術的
So starting from when I was little
所以從我很小的時候開始
Every year my family
我們家每年都會一起
did puZZles of famous paintings
拼一些名畫拼圖
But lately it's just me, by myself
但是，最近都只有我一個人在拼了
Can I help you?
小朋友需要幫忙嗎
I want to buy 'Starry Night'
我想要買星空
Starry Night
星空啊
We have it in 300, 500
我們星空有三百五百
1 000 and 3000 pieces
一千還有三千片的
Which one do you want?
妳要哪一種
I have the 1 000 pieces
我們家的星空是一千片的
But I lost a piece
但是我不小心掉了一片
Can you sell me one piece?
能不能就賣我一片
The center of the brightest star
就最亮星星中間那一片
We don't sell individual pieces
我們沒有只賣一片的
But, besides that
那要不然這樣
Feel free to look around
妳自己先隨便看看
You know the origin of the jigsaw puZZle?
妳知道拼圖的由來嗎
No
不知道
In 1 760
在1760年
There was an English mapmaker
有一位專門設計地圖的英國人
He stuck one of his maps
他把畫好的地圖
onto a wooden board
貼在一塊木板上
Then cut around the borders of the towns
然後沿著鄉村都市一塊一塊的割下來
And had his kids put it back together
然後再拿給小朋友拼
When they were done
小朋友拼久了之後
They knew where they lived, where home is
就會知道他們是住在哪個鄉村哪個都市
And that's the world's
所以這也是世界上
first jigsaw puZZle
第一個拼圖
How do you know this?
你怎麼會知道這個
It's over there
那邊寫的
You're silly!
你白癡喔
It's written on there
就上面寫的
And you memoriZed it?
那你還背下來
My memory's good
我記性好
Then
那
Say it again
再背一遍
One day
有一天
He stuck a map onto some wood
他把一張地圖貼在一個木板上
And then
然後
He cut out the borders of the towns
就沿著鄉村跟都市的邊緣
Piece by piece
一塊一塊剪下來
And his kids put them back together
再拿給小孩子去拼
So
所以說
The world's first jigsaw
世界上第一幅拼圖
Mom
媽
You're not listening
妳沒有在聽
Mei
小美
If you're done eating, go to your room
吃飽了先回房間
I need to talk to your father
我有話要跟爸說
Let's go
走吧
We'll know tomorrow
會不會得獎
if we win or not
明天就知道結果了
What's wrong?
怎麼了
Do you think
你覺得
The love between two people
兩個人之間的愛
can disappear?
會消失嗎
Yes
會
What can be done?
那怎麼辦
I don't know
不知道
Stay with me a bit longer
再陪我一下好不好
This one's quite good
這個還蠻好看的
Yeah!  nice colors
對啊！配色還不錯
This one
這個
Not bad
還不錯啊
You like this one?
你喜歡這個
No, no
沒有啦
It's ugly
很難看
I can't believe this one
怎麼會這樣啊
'Roo' of Honor?
歡，榮舉榜
Let's go see class 3
快去三班看
So many people
好多人在那邊看
Yeah, so many
對呀！好多人喔
Shawn!
陳威翔
Stop it!
不要打了
Get him off!
快把他拉走
Quickly!
快
Stop it!
不要打了
Get out of the way!
走開啦
Go away!  stop crowding!
趕快回去啦！還看
Mom
媽
We're moving again?
又要搬家了
He's come back
那個人又出現了
Here, help mom with this
這幫媽拿一下
We'll talk inside
我們上去再說
Mei, stop that
小美，停一下
Mei!
謝欣美
Mom and Dad
爸爸跟媽媽
We
我們…
Mom and Dad are getting divorced
爸爸媽媽決定要離婚了
Mei, you're 1 3
小美已經十三歲了
You understand, right?
應該聽得懂吧
Mei's 1 3, Mei understands
小美十三歲，聽得懂
We spent a long time
爸媽討論了很久
Making this decision
做了這個決定
This is best for everyone
這樣對大家都好
This is between Mom and Dad
這是爸爸媽媽之間的問題
It's nothing to do with you
跟小美無關
Don't think it's your fault
絕對不要認為自己有錯
It's just that Mom and Dad
只是爸爸媽媽
Can't live together anymore
沒有辦法在一起生活了
We don't want to keep fighting
我們也不想一直吵架
It's not fair to Mei
這樣對小美也不公平
After the divorce
離婚以後
Mom will move out
媽會搬出去
You're in middle school now
爸媽都覺得妳已經上中學了
You can decide who you want to live with
應該讓妳自己選擇要跟誰住
You don't have to make a decision now
當然也不用現在下決定
And I won't move out right away
媽也不會馬上搬出去
There's still a lot of things to sort out
還有很多事的細節之後可以慢慢處理
We just thought
只是我們都覺得
We should let you know
應該要讓妳先知道
Mei
小美
No rush
不急
You can take your time
小美可以慢慢想
What are you doing?
妳在幹嘛
So did you decide?
妳做好決定了嗎
If Grandpa were still alive
要是我爺爺還在的話
They wouldn't be doing this
他們就不會這樣了
When did you last see the stars?
你上次看星星是什麼時候
I don't remember
我不記得了
Let's go look at the stars
我們一起去看星星好不好
There's a truck!
有車耶
What's up?
怎麼啦
We're going to my Grandpa's house
我們要去我爺爺家
Can we hitch a ride?
可以搭個便車嗎
It's this way?
這個方向
Yes
嗯
Hop on
好，上來
Ride as far as you like
走多遠算多遠
Thanks
謝謝
Careful
小心
Bye bye!
拜拜
When I was 6
我六歲的時候
My first day at school
第一天上國小
This really embarrassing thing happened
就發生了一件超糢的事情
Here
來
I took my lunchbox
就是中午拿好便當
And I went into the wrong classroom
就進錯教室
When I was 8
我八歲那一年
I saw this girl playing piano on the TV
有一次在電視上看到一個彈鋼琴的女生
And I thought she was really beautiful
那時候就覺得女生彈鋼琴好漂亮喔
On my 9th birthday
我九歲那一年生日
I made my own birthday cake
蛋糕是我自己做的
It was a big green tea cake
是一個超大的抹茶紅豆蛋糕
When I finished, I thought it was ugly
我做完之後覺得它蠻醜的
But I took it to school
可是我帶去學校
And my classmates ate it all
同學就把它搶光光耶
I didn't get a single bite
我自己一口都沒有吃到
Last time I climbed this mountain
我上次上山看爺爺
Was summer vacation two years ago
是兩年前的暑假
In this stream
這溪流
When I played with Grandpa
我跟爺爺在玩的時候
Am I talking too much?
我是不是話說太多了
No
不會啊
You say something
那該你說囉
I don't have anything to say
我沒有什麼好說的耶
Impossible
怎麼可能
Everyone has stories
每個人小時候
from when they were little
都會有印象深刻的事情
I don't
我沒有
Stingy
小氣
I'm not
我哪有
You big stingy
小氣鬼
I'm not stingy
我不是小氣鬼
Yes you are!
明明就是
Hey!
欸
I think it's this way
我記得是這邊
Looks like the path on the right
應該是右邊這一條吧
I think
好像…
No one's walked that path for a while
那一條看起來像是沒有人在走的
But I remember it being on the left
但我真的記得是左邊
You're sure?
妳確定嗎
Yes
嗯
It must be here
應該是這邊
I remember these trees
我記得這兩棵大樹
Ah!
啊
What's that!
那是什麼
It's nothing
沒事
Don't look, let's go
不要看，我們走
What shall we do?
怎麼辦
Where are we?
這裡是哪裡啊
Look!
妳看
There's a house!
那邊有房子
Anyone here?
有人在嗎
What?
怎麼了
I want to change clothes too
我也想換衣服
Didn't you bring any?
妳沒帶衣服嗎
I'll go outside
我去外面
Call me when you're done
妳換好再告訴我
No, don't leave!
你不要出去
I'm scared
我會害怕
Don't turn round!
不可以轉過來喔
OK
好
You're still there?
你還在嗎
I'm   I'm still here
還在啊…
Jay!
周宇傑
Pervert
色耶
Jay?
小傑
Yeah
嗯
Do you think, if we die
如果我們兩個
Out here in the mountains
就這樣死在山裡面
When people find us
別人發現我們的時候
They'll say we died for love?
他們會不會說我們是殉情
You're silly!
你白癡喔
I said 'if"
我說如果嘛
We're not going to die
我們不會死啦
But your Mom and Dad
倒是妳
Must be really worried about you
妳爸爸媽媽現在應該很擔心妳吧
Who knows
說不定
Maybe they haven't even noticed I'm gone
他們到現在還沒發現我離開了
That's not possible
怎麼可能
One time, last year
去年有一次
They had a huge fight
我爸媽吵架吵得很兇
And I wanted to come see Grandpa
我就很想去山上找我爺爺
I went to the train station
就一個人到火車站
And sat there for ages
在那邊坐了很久
Finally, I went home
最後我還是回家了
But when I got back
但是等我到家的時候
They were just in their rooms
爸媽還在各自房間裡
With no idea I'd been gone
根本沒有發現我離開過
When I was 9
我九歲那一年
My dad had an accident in his factory
我爸爸在工廠發生了意外
And lost his fingers
壓斷了手指
He stayed home every day, drinking
他就天天待在家喝酒
gambling
賭博
He started to hit my mom
還開始打我媽媽
He would grab her by the hair
把我媽媽的頭髮抓起來
and keep on slapping her
一直賞巴掌
One day
有一天
My dad was drunk
我爸喝醉了
He wanted me to drink with him
他要我陪他喝酒
I refused
我說我不要
So he took all my awards
他就把我所有的獎狀
And ripped them all up
一張一張的撕掉
I couldn't help it, I started to cry
我忍不住就哭了
Then he started to hit me
我爸就開始打我
He said I looked down on him
他說我瞧不起他
I didn't look down on him
可是我沒有瞧不起他
I just wanted a normal dad
我不過是想要一個正常的好爸爸
Why did I have to get a dad like this?
為什麼我要有這樣的爸爸
When my mom found out
這件事被我媽知道後
We ran away from home
他就帶我搬離那個家
And moved far away
搬到很遠的地方
But not long after, Dad found us
但是沒多久又被我爸找到了
So we kept on moving
所以我們就一直搬家
And moving
一直搬家
You're actually lucky
妳很幸福了
Get up
起來一下
Come on
來嘛
Why?
怎麼了
Come here
過來啊
Dance with me
跟我跳舞
I
啊…
I'll teach you
我教你，這樣
1  2 3 4 5  Jump!
一二三四五跳
1  2 3  Kick, clap!
一二三踢，拍
Same this side
這邊也是
Kick, clap!
踢，拍
What dance is this?
這什麼舞
I don't know
我也不知道耶
My mom learnt it from an old movie
是我媽媽從部老電影學來的
OK
那…
Watch me first
先看我跳一遍好了
1  2 3 4 5 Jump!
一二三四五跳
1  2 3 4
一二三四
Three steps forward
往前三步
Turn!
轉
1  2 3 Jump!
一二三跳
Same this side
這邊也是
Kick   Clap
踢，拍
Three steps forward
往前三步
Then like this
然後這樣
Good morning
早安
Morning
早
Sleep well?
睡得好嗎
Yeah
嗯
Today we should follow the tracks
我們今天就沿著這軌道走
They should lead to the road
應該就可以找到路了
OK
嗯
Jay
小傑
Thank you
謝謝你
Huh, here again
欸，又是這裡
Ladies first
女士優先
You first!
你先
No, you first!
妳先請
I insist, you first
沒有關係，妳先
Let's go!
走了啦
Almost there
快到了
You can tell by smelling the leaves
你聞葉子就知道了
Trust me
相信我
Look!
你看
Wait for me outside
你在門口等我一下
Is that OK?
可以嗎
Sure
好
Jay
小傑
Come in
進來吧
OK
好
This is Grandpa's workbench
這是爺爺的工作檯
He made all of these
這些都是他做的
I painted these when I was little
這些畫是我很小的時候畫的
This is my little desk
這是我的小書桌
Here it is
就是這邊
When I was little
小時候
I came with Grandpa to look at the stars
跟爺爺看星空的地方
Why won't the mist go away?
怎麼霧還不散
Give it time
再等一下吧
I really hope
我真的好希望
You can see the stars
你能看到星空
Mei
小美
For this short time
這段時間
I've been so happy
我真的很開心
I never knew I could be so happy
我從來都不知道我可以這麼開心
Knowing you
認識妳
Now I know
我才知道
I can be lucky, too
我可以這麼幸福
When I get home
回家後
I have to move again
我又要搬家了
My dad, he
我爸爸他…
Mei
小美
Your Grandpa's phone is cut off
你爺爺的電話已經不能用了
I brought a cell phone
我有帶手機
In my backpack
在我包包裡
Sorry
對不起
I didn't mean to not tell you
我不是故意不讓你知道
It's just
只是
If we used the cell phone
如果要用到手機
Our journey would have come to an end
我們的旅程就要結束了
Let's go home
我們回家吧
Jay
小傑
Stay with me, OK?
再陪我一下好不好
Jay!
周宇傑
Jay
小傑
Dad!
爸
Mon!
媽
Grandpa
爺爺
Mei
小美
I have a mom and dad who love me
我有一對愛我的爸爸媽媽
Even though
雖然
they don't love each other anymore
他們已經不愛彼此了
I have classmates who care about me
我有一群關心我的同學
Even though
雖然
they don't always understand me
她們不見得瞭解我
Looking at my classmates walking away
看著我同學們的背影
I realiZed
我發現
Their summer was just starting
她們的夏天才正要開始
But my summer
但我的夏天
Was already over
卻提早結束了
In my first year of high school
在我高一那一年
My mom and dad got divorced
爸爸媽媽還是離婚了
A few years later
媽媽幾年後
Mom went abroad and re-married
在國外再嫁
I chose to stay with Dad
我，選擇了跟爸爸繼續生活
At 1 3
十三歲的我們
We're very fragile
其實非常月危弱
We're also very tough
其實也相當堅強
So
所以
Before we have to face this cruel world
在我們必須面對這個殘酷的世界以前
Please be gentle with us
請溫柔的對待我們
We don't ask for much
我們要求的真的不多
A glance
一個眼神
A kind word
一句話
A rainstorm
一場雨
A gust of wind
一陣風
or
或者
Just a nod of the head goodbye
只是一個點頭再見
It's these little kindnesses
只要這麼一點點的溫暖
That make us feel special
我們都會打從心裡感到幸福
But in the end
但是，我要的再見
I never got the goodbye I wanted
卻始終都沒有得到
After that
後來
I never saw Jay again
我再也沒有見到小傑
The little rabbit
小兔子
never turned into a big rabbit
再也沒有變成大兔子
The little elephant
小象
never turned into a big elephant
也沒有變成大象
The only thing that grew
唯一長大的
was me
好像只有我自己
Everything passes
雖然一切都會過去
But before letting go
但是，在放手之前
Hold on, as tight as you can
想要抓多緊，就抓多緊
Mei!
小美
Merry Christmas!
聖誕快樂
Are you happy?
妳開心嗎
Yeah
開心
Let's take a walk!
我們去逛逛吧
OK
好
Happy at school?
在學校開心嗎
Yeah
開心
You've made friends?
有交到朋友嗎
How many?
幾個
Five
五個
Do you hear that?
有沒有聽到
Yes
有
So beautiful!
好美喔
It's Mommy
是媽媽
Mommy, where are you?
媽媽，妳在哪
I'm with big sister
我跟姊姊在逛街
She bought me lots of presents!
姊姊買好多禮物給我
OK
好的
See you soon
等一下見
Bye bye, Mommy
媽媽拜拜
Hi, MOm
喂，媽
Everything's good
我跟妹妹都很好
Yes
嗯
She's being good
她很乖
Mom, it's no problem
媽，妳跟我客氣什麼
Mom, it's snowing
下雪了
Did you pick up Dad?
接到爸啦
No need
不用了
I'll see you guys at dinner
待會就要一起吃飯了
What you looking at?
妳在看什麼
Why is it missing a piece?
為什麼這個畫缺了一片
Mom
媽
See you in a bit
待會見
Yes
嗯
Merry Christmas
聖誕快樂
Can I help you?
妳需要什麼
Do you still remember?
你還記得嗎
That summer
那年夏天
That most splendid
最燦爛
Most lonely of starry nights
最寂寞的星空